[♪ adventurous music plays]
[Lo'ak] Come on, Bro.
[laughs]
Whoo! Whoo, whoo, whoo!
[chuckles]
Whoo! [chuckles]
[Lo'ak ululates]
Whoo!
Whoa. Whoa.
Hey, watch it.
You were in my way, Bro.
Oh, okay.
- [Lo'ak] Whoo...
- [shrieks]
Whoo!
[grunts]
[chuckles] Is that all you got?
You want to go faster, huh?
[chuckles] Whoo-hoo!
- [both panting]
- [ikran squawk]
That was cool, Bro.
[chuckles] Skxawng, let go.
It was cool riding
with you, Bro.
High four.
[sighs]
- [scoffs]
- [chuckles]
[sighs]
All right,
I got to get back, Bro.
Little Brother,
tell me one thing before you go.
How did I die?
You got shot.
We could have escaped, but I
made us go back for Spider.
Then we had to go back.
That's not your fault.
Tell that to Dad.
We weren't even supposed
to be out there.
I got us caught
because I disobeyed orders.
That's just you, Little Bro.
I love you, Brother.
Skxawng.
[Lo'ak] I killed my brother.
No matter what happens,
I have to live with that
for the rest of my life.
[panting]
I wish I could do it.
No, I wish I could do it.
If I have another
stupid seizure underwater...
Yeah,
you'd be me without a mask.
[imitates choking]
- Uh, let's test that.
- Hey, hey.
- Watch it.
- See what happens.
Hey, watch the stitches.
Uh-huh. Yeah,
how do you like that, huh?
- No! Ow! [shrieks]
- [laughs]
[♪ Neytiri singing in Na'vi]
[Lo'ak] The fire of hate
leaves only the ash of grief.
My mother mourned
the ancient way,
singing her son's life
during the daily eclipse.
Because the light
always returns.
[singing fades]
[Lo'ak] There's the Na'vi way,
and then there's my dad's way.
Say nothing.
Keep busy.
[breathes heavily]
[ilu shrieks]
[Lo'ak] The Reef People say
the sea washes you clean.
Washes away your sins.
[ilu squeaks]
What do you got?
You're supposed
to be collecting guns.
That thing's useless.
Focus, boy.
Don't let your mother see that.
Hey, excuse me.
- Sorry. [laughs]
- Excuse me.
- Tuk.
- [Tuk] Sorry.
Bro.
Ah, sick.
What is this?
Tsireya?
What are you doing?
This is an AR, all right?
This is the mag.
It's where the bullets are.
Empty.
Slap it.
Rack it.
And then, boom,
you can just spray.
[chuckles] You can kill
a lot of Sky People with this.
See? Ceramic action.
You clean 'em and oil 'em,
be as good as new.
This is not the Na'vi way,
Jakesully.
Weapons of metal are forbidden.
You know this.
To touch them
poisons the heart.
Eywa
will provide.
[sighs] Right.
The mourning period
is not even over.
Tuk.
[Ronal] You should be
with your family,
not gathering these things.
Your woman
needs you.
My son lies with the ancestors
in the reef.
This is our home.
I said I would stand and fight,
but I can't fight gunships
with spears.
We sank the demon ship.
The pink skins fear us now.
Yeah? We got lucky.
And they got many more ships.
Least we got these.
We are grateful you
stand with us, Jakesully.
It is not guns we need.
It is Rider of Last Shadow.
Ride great toruk
as you did before.
[inhales deeply]
When you ride the beast,
you become the beast.
And the more blood, the better.
I will not become
Toruk Makto again.
Jakesully,
you are always Toruk Makto.
Come. Rotxo.
Can you hear me?
[Scoresby] Yeah, we can
hear you loud and clear.
Go on, Doc.
So, uh, we've been through
the wreck, inside and out.
Uh, we've searched to about
a 200-meter radius around it.
We didn't find any Na'vi bodies.
Just crew or...
what's left of 'em.
Well, keep looking, Doctor.
- Expand the search radius.
- [Dr. Garvin] Roger that.
Of note though,
I did find an interesting
new algae.
Hello? Can you hear me?
- Sully is still out there.
- [Ardmore] We don't know that.
Scavengers could have
carried off the bodies.
Nope. He made it out.
And he's in this area.
Down to a handful of villages.
You just give me a ship
and I'll...
I gave you a ship.
It's right there, on the bottom.
Yeah. Along with my crew.
All dead.
You brought me out here,
twenty-six trillion miles,
for a single mission,
a kinetic hard kill op
against one guy.
I ain't backing off.
[Dr. Garvin]
Are we still connected? Hello?
Do they have me on mute?
The spirit of my ancestors
is in this bow.
It was our strength.
I can help you fix it, Lo'ak.
No!
It's ruined!
[Lo'ak] Everything I touch
gets ruined.
They never talked about it.
But it was there in the room.
Like a crouching thanator.
[sighs]
I know you will never
give up your bow.
So...
Just don't be close
when it hits.
[sighs]
[breathing shakily]
So, you agree with Ronal?
I will never speak against
my husband
in front of that woman.
Look, I'm a marine.
I'm not taking a knife
to a gunfight.
Or a prayer. [scoffs]
So, what am I supposed to do?
I can't run.
I can't fight.
Oh, that's right.
Eywa will provide. Yeah?
So, where was Eywa?
Where was Eywa when our son...
Jake!
I'm in this place
where I have nothing.
Not my people, not my forest.
Even my father's bow is gone.
All I have...
is my faith
that this is
the Great Mother's plan.
[breathing shakily]
You have this family.
And you have me.
And I love you so much.
[sobs]
[chittering]
[♪ adventurous music plays]
[bellows]
[whistles]
Yeah, Payakan, you're the man!
[rumbles]
[tulkun vocalizing]
Whoa. Bro, Bro.
[exclaims]
This is sick! [laughs]
- Whoo! Whoo!
- Whoo-hoo!
Whoo!
- [laughs]
- [screams]
- Whoo! [laughs]
- Bro, come on! Go, go, go, go!
- Oh, sh...
- Yeah!
That was insane, cuz.
I know, right, Bro?
[Tsireya laughs]
I thought you were dead.
[both imitate splash, laugh]
It sucks that Payakan
is still an outcast.
Yeah. After saving
all our asses.
No.
I'm sorry,
but by the tulkun way,
he bears the deaths.
[Payakan rumbling]
All those
who died in the battle.
He bears those deaths.
I'm sorry. You saved us all.
[rumbling] No matter.
We are Brothers.
[distorted] Forever, Brother.
[normal] Always.
[bellows]
[exo-pack beeping]
[gasping, choking]
Dad!
- Wait, where's the spare?
- It's in the basket, I think.
Hey! Wake up! Where is it?
- Hey! Where's the spare mask?
- What?
Where's the spare mask?
Used to be there. Where is it?
- I don't know.
- Find it.
- It's not here.
- Speak to me. Where is it?
- [Kiri] I can't find it.
- [Jake] Hey, hey! Where is it?
- Come on. Come on. Come on.
- I got it. Dad.
- Dad. I found it.
- Hurry.
[beeping stops]
- [breathing heavily]
- [air hisses]
Spider, no.
Breathe.
- Breathe.
[Jake] Deep and slow.
Deep and slow.
There you go.
You're okay.
[breathing deeply] I'm good.
I'm good. I'm okay.
Skxawng.
You have to be careful.
- Careful's my middle name.
- Yeah, skxawng.
You should be more careful,
little baby.
Pay attention.
- Get off. Get off. Get off.
- Stupid is your middle name.
- Be careful, little baby.
- No, let him go.
- You have to pay attention.
- Skxawng is his middle name.
- Are you sure you're okay?
- Yeah, I feel fine.
[horn blowing]
[Tsireya] The Windtraders.
- The Windtraders are here.
- [Na'vi cheering]
The Windtraders are coming.
Come on!
Come on. Let's go.
- [Tsireya] Come on.
- [Tuk laughs]
Come on, Tuk.
[♪ joyful music plays]
[Lo'ak] Whoo!
[whoops]
Hey! [whooping]
[Na'vi chattering,
playing music]
Tsireya.
[gasps]
Look. [chuckles]
Look at him.
He's not going
to take up much room.
As long as he's no trouble.
- Take a knee. Let's go. Tuk.
- Kiri.
- Come on, Kiri.
- What?
- Kiri, please.
- Children, please sit down.
[Jake] Please, sit.
Your mother and I have
come to a decision.
[sighs]
Spider, you're going to live
back in High Camp with Norm.
- What?
- The Windtraders will take you.
- No, Dad.
- No, Dad. He can't.
Spider, you can't live in a mask
day and night.
I just want
to stay here with you.
- I know, but it's too risky.
- This isn't fair.
Please. You're the only family
I've ever known.
[Jake] This is what's
best for you.
But, Dad, he's our best friend.
Can't we just find a way?
[Jake] It's too dangerous.
You're one dead battery away
from being dead yourself.
He belongs with his own kind.
Mom.
And what kind
is that, Mother? Alien?
- Kiri.
- Pink-ass.
- Stop.
You hate them so much,
that's all you see.
It's Spider.
Please, Jake.
Mr. Sully, I won't be
any problem. You know that.
Dad, this isn't right.
Spider is part of this family.
He will never
- be a part of this family.
- Mother, no.
[Kiri sobs]
The caravan is the safest way
to move him.
- No, please.
- He's going today.
- You can't do this. Dad, he's...
- It's a done deal.
Enough! This is a family.
It's not a democracy.
All right?
I hate you!
This is what is best, baby girl.
- No!
- Hey, it's okay.
Don't touch me!
- Hey. It's okay.
- [sobs]
- [Jake] You understand?
- No.
I already lost my brother.
I can't lose anyone else.
[hisses]
[Lo'ak] Sullys stick together.
[Jake sighs]
[Lo'ak] Yep, that's
the family motto.
- It's bullshit.
- This isn't fair.
[Jake] Okay, okay.
Hey. All right.
How about this?
We all go together
to drop him off.
Kiri.
You said you wanted to see
your grandmother.
Yeah, it will be an adventure.
For the whole family.
Yeah. Cool.
[shrieks]
[Jake] Hey, stay here.
Our arrangement was
for the pink-skinned boy only.
We won't be any trouble.
You are already trouble.
A trader must move freely.
We cannot choose sides.
Having Toruk Makto on board
cuts very close to
choosing a side in this war.
Yeah, but you're mistaken.
Toruk Makto
was never on your ship.
But if he was ever
aboard, then...
him and his woman would be
happy to fly as outriders
and protect your caravan.
Perhaps so.
The Mangkwan raiders
grow more aggressive.
[Jake] Hmm.
Very well.
I meet you on this.
[sighs]
- [horn blowing]
- [♪ adventurous music plays]
Cast off!
Come on.
Cast off below!
[♪ singing in Na'vi]
Lo'ak! [chuckles] Lo'ak!
Oh, Tsireya!
Tsireya!
Lo'ak! [chuckles]
Ready about!
[crew member 1]
Ready about! On all lines.
[Peylak] Bow to starboard.
Windward vanes out full!
Haul out and raise
full to windward!
[crew members] Heave!
Heave!
Lighten ship. Come up easy.
Windward out full!
[chuckles]
Make all and set taut!
[♪ Windtraders
singing in Na'vi]
Whoo! Yeah!
[Lo'ak] Everyone mourns
in their own way.
For me,
it's being up here alone.
I feel him with me.
Bro, check it out.
[Lo'ak] I hear his voice
in the wind.
[ululates]
[squawks]
[Jake sighs]
Hold this.
- Hey, Dad, I've been thinking.
- Yeah?
I should carry a rifle.
And I could fly with you.
Yeah.
That's gonna happen. [grunts]
Why not?
You trained me to shoot, okay?
I know what I'm doing.
Yeah? Where's your comms?
I called you like five times.
Wear your comms.
That's rule number one.
You can't even do that.
[groans]
[Wainfleet]
Bring up the next one.
That's it.
What you got?
So, I promised this guy
on imaging
a case of beer if he
ever got something for us.
Long-range patrols
clocked these guys
when they punched our airspace.
A routine flyby.
Here's the enhanced.
Smile, bitches.
- When? [clicks tongue]
- 1350 today.
I got coordinates.
Let's mount up.
Thank you.
[horn blowing]
Haul in hard!
Steady on course.
[exo-pack beeping]
[beeping stops]
Your pack.
I'm good.
I got plenty of time.
Clear ahead.
Jake!
Mangkwan!
[♪ suspenseful music plays]
Mangkwan raiders.
Weapons up.
Sound the alarm!
[shouts]
[ululating]
- [Jake] Weapons up!
- Kiri, go.
- Run!
- Go.
Get these out.
Come on, let's go.
Let's go. To cover.
[grunts]
[shouts]
[shrieks]
[grunts]
Go, go.
Protect your sisters.
Can you do that?
Yes, sir.
Stay under cover.
[crew member]
Repel boarders!
[Jake shouts]
[shouts]
[panting]
[shrieks]
Spider, here.
Shit, my comms.
[grunts]
- [grunting]
- [groans]
Stay with the girls. [coughs]
Bro, where are you going?
Bro, you're supposed
to stay here.
[shrieks]
[grunts]
[shouts]
- [grunts]
- [shrieks]
[shouts]
Come on.
Release.
[grunting]
- [grunts]
- [shrieks]
[pants]
[shrieks]
[breathing heavily]
[ululates]
[Spider] Get back.
- Get back.
- [gasps]
[shouts]
- [grunts]
[groaning]
- [shouts]
- [grunting]
[groans]
[shouts]
[grunting]
[both grunting]
[panting]
[grunts, shouts]
[grunts]
[shrieks]
[grunts, exhales sharply]
[shouts]
I am
the fire!
[shouting]
[snarls]
[shouts]
[grunts]
[shouting]
Oh, sh...
[grunts]
Hey!
[groans]
[shouts]
[grunts]
[groans]
[shouts]
[groans, shouts]
[shrieks]
[both grunting]
[grunts, shouts]
- [shouts]
- [grunts]
- [Kiri] Tuk.
- Go. Go.
Climb. Climb.
Get up. Hurry.
[exclaims]
[shrieks]
[groans] Spider, grab on.
Come on, let's go.
Hold on.
[grunts]
[♪ dramatic music plays]
[scoffs]
[gasping]
Neytiri, Neytiri, do you copy?
[screeching]
Crap, crap, crap, crap, crap.
- Guys, it's Lo'ak.
- Where?
Come on.
We gotta get him. Go. Go.
Lo'ak.
- Jump.
- Bro, come on. Jump.
Now!
[grunts] Go, go, go, go, go.
Hold on, everyone.
[shouting, grunting]
Hold on, Lo'ak.
[shrieks, shouts]
- [gasps]
- [shrieks]
[Tuk, Kiri scream]
[grunting]
[grunts] Hold on. Tuk!
[grunting, panting]
[whimpering]
- Spider, my leg.
- [Spider] Kiri.
[groans]
Pull.
- You okay?
- Tuk.
Okay. You're okay.
Tuk, Tuk. Hey.
- Hey, are you okay?
- [panting]
- Bro, you good?
- Yeah, I'm good.
My sweet girl.
Sweet girl.
I'm so sorry.
- It's okay.
- Thank you.
[people screaming in distance]
- Shit.
Bro, my spare's on the ship.
What?
My backup's on that ship.
Shit. Kiri, stay here.
[breathing heavily]
[screaming in distance]
[exo-pack beeps]
- [screaming, clamoring]
- [♪ tense music plays]
[gasps, shrieks]
- [snarls]
- [exo-pack beeps]
- [grunts]
- [shouts]
[grunts]
[shouting]
- [sobs]
- [exo-pack beeps]
[chanting]
Look. After them!
- We gotta go. We gotta go.
- Shit.
Come on, we gotta go.
Kiri, run. Kiri, come on.
They're coming.
Go, go.
[ululating]
They're coming. Come on.
Let's go.
Keep going.
Go, go, go, go, go.
- Kiri, come on. This way.
- Come on, Tuk.
- [Spider] Come on.
- Hurry.
[ululating, shrieking]
- [grunts]
- [shouts]
[breathes shakily]
[panting]
- Keep going. Keep going.
- Hurry.
- [raider] What happened?
- Turn.
One goes through.
Tsahìk, look.
Knife.
On me.
- Come on.
- Tuk, here.
[raider ululating]
There!
[raiders ululating]
- They're coming.
- Tuk.
Kiri, come on.
This way. Go, go.
Keep going.
- Come on, Tuk. This way.
- Hurry. Hurry.
Gotta get in the water. Come on.
Go, go, go, go. Come on.
- Come on, come on.
- Lo'ak!
Come on, swim!
[Tuk] Lo'ak!
I got you, Tuk. It's okay.
What does Dad always say?
Sullys stick together.
No, the other one.
- Sullys never quit.
- That's right.
Sullys never quit.
[grunts] Nothing.
Kiri.
- Lo'ak. Lo'ak.
- Tuk, hold on.
Hold on.
[screams]
[grunting]
Kiri.
Spider.
I'm fine.
Grab my hand.
[grunting]
Eagle Eye, do you copy?
Lo'ak. Come in, boy,
answer me.
Neytiri, how copy?
Neytiri, Neytiri,
how copy?
Neytiri, do you copy?
What...
Tuk.
Swim.
Go.
- Grab onto a rock.
- [Lo'ak] Come on.
I got you, Tuk.
I got you.
[air hisses]
- Is everybody okay?
- Here you go.
You okay?
Spider, you okay, Bro?
Yeah, I'm good.
[panting]
- Do you see them?
- [Tuk coughs]
No. Let's get out of sight.
I wanna go home.
[Lo'ak] Tuk, come on.
- I'm tired, and I'm hungry.
- I know.
- I wanna go home.
- I am too. We'll go home.
Dad has no idea where we are.
We've got no comms.
- We're on our own.
- [exo-pack beeps]
Bro, I've got to get a mask.
What...
What are we gonna do?
I don't know.
Why am I in charge?
Calm down.
We have to do something.
- [exo-pack beeps]
- Shut up.
- Lo'ak.
- Crap.
Crap, crap, crap,
crap, crap, crap.
We have to go back to the ship.
No, we can't go back
to the ship.
Those guys are between us
and the ship.
No, that's our
last known position.
That's where Dad
is gonna be looking for us.
- Bro, no.
- We'll just circle around them.
It's a good idea.
Which way?
This way. Come on.
Everyone, follow me.
[Jake breathing heavily]
[Quaritch]
It's all over, Jake.
- [grunts]
- [gunfire]
You stay real still now.
[grunts]
Is that all you got?
All right. That'll do.
Still a smart-ass, huh?
Let's see those hands.
Hands.
I... I killed you.
I guess I don't die
that easy, Corporal.
[groans]
Help me.
- [shrieks]
- [Neytiri groans]
[coughing]
[spits, sniffs]
Who hit you, Corporal?
Mangkwan raiders.
They call themselves
"Ash People."
[Quaritch] What's this?
They cut the kuru.
They take their enemies' to'a,
their power.
That's worse than death
to these guys.
Any sign of 'em?
Kids are gone.
That's fully charged,
which means he missed
his mask change,
and he's running out.
And that's if these Ash People
don't get to him first.
We gotta go after
these kids right now,
or you're never gonna
see him again.
Can you track 'em?
That is not the mission.
What are we doing?
Can you track 'em?
We're burning time, Colonel.
Boss, we got him.
We're outta here.
No, the cuffs stay.
Which way?
[sighs]
Oh, you're gonna get me killed.
Again.
Come on. This way.
- [Spider gasping, choking]
- [exo-pack beeping]
The river's got to be
just up ahead. Come on.
- [gasping, choking continues]
- [beeping continues]
Spider.
Bro.
- That's not good.
- What can we do?
Monkey Boy, conserve your air.
Look at me.
Take slow breaths.
Lo'ak...
- can you carry him?
- Yeah, yeah.
Come on, Bro. Horsey rides.
Hop up.
[groans, breathing heavily]
[groans]
[sobbing]
The kids went in the water.
Smart move.
- [Spider gasping, choking]
- [exo-pack beeping]
- No.
- No, no, no, no, no.
No, no, no.
- Bro.
- Oh, no, no, no. Spider.
Great Mother,
save this Sky Person.
I beg you.
We don't have time for praying.
- He's dying.
- Please.
It's okay.
It's gonna be okay, buddy.
Just breathe.
Kiri.
Kiri, we need to go.
Come on.
[distorted] Come on,
we have to go.
We can't sit around here.
We have to keep going.
We're almost there.
We can't sit around here.
[normal] We have to go.
Tuk, go get her.
Kiri, come on.
[groans]
[breathing heavily]
Stop.
Bring him. Here.
[Lo'ak] Kiri, stop.
- Quickly.
- Stop.
[echoing] Do as I say.
[normal] Put him here.
[breathing heavily]
[Spider wheezes]
[exo-pack beeping]
[Spider choking]
[Lo'ak] Stop.
Kiri, what are you doing?
What are you doing?
I'm not sure.
This feels right.
What?
Be quiet. I can't talk.
[groans]
[gasping weakly]
- [gasping stops]
- [Kiri sighs]
Lo'ak. Lo'ak.
[Kiri breathes rhythmically]
[gasping weakly resumes]
[beeping intensifies]
[steady beep]
His mask.
Take it off.
- What?
- He can't breathe.
Come on.
[♪ dramatic music plays]
[panting, moaning rhythmically]
[panting, moaning intensifies]
Kiri.
Kiri, Kiri.
- Kiri, Kiri.
- [moaning]
Lo'ak, no.
[Kiri cries]
Oh, no.
I'm so sorry.
I'm sorry.
[crying]
I'm so sorry.
[gasps, coughing]
Spider.
[breathing heavily]
[groans, spits]
I'm breathing?
Yes, Monkey Boy.
You are.
[Kiri chuckles]
I'm dead.
This is the Spirit World.
No, cuz.
You're still here.
[breathes deeply]
I'm breathing the air.
Yeah.
I'm breathing the air!
I guess I don't need
this bullshit anymore.
Whoo!
Yeah, I'm breathing the air,
baby!
Bro, Bro, quiet. Quiet.
Thank you.
[Kiri] Spider.
Whatever you did. Thank you.
Shit. Get back.
Kiri.
Stay behind me.
[raiders ululating, shouting]
We're cut off.
[Spider] Bro!
[Tuk] Behind us.
- [shouts]
- [Spider hisses]
[Tuk screams]
[hisses, grunts]
No!
Kiri!
[raider] Tsahìk.
Ah.
[Kiri sobbing]
How is he breathing
with no mask?
I can't even think about that
right now.
We gotta get in there.
Is not our air
poison
to Sky People?
[snarls]
How
do you still live,
air breather?
[snarls]
Because it is the will of Eywa.
[raiders snarl]
Eywa?
Yes.
If I cut now,
do you think Eywa
will come to save him?
Come on.
Get these off me.
They're gonna kill him.
Do you think?
[raiders laugh, snarl]
No.
Your goddess
has no dominion here.
Come on.
Now give me the knife.
Colonel.
You...
will show me how this works.
Show me how to make thunder.
I can't.
It's empty.
No thunder.
[Varang] Make thunder.
[Lo'ak] I can't.
It's empty.
Make it work.
[Lo'ak] I'm telling you,
I'm telling you...
there's no thunder.
Kill the youngest one.
No, no, no, no, no.
Please.
- Please. Stop.
- No.
[shouts, grunting]
[raiders grunting, ululating]
Weapons down!
[screams]
Down!
Mangkwan!
Now get back. Back.
- [Tuk] Dad.
- [Jake] Go on.
[snarls]
Stay back.
Get back.
- Dad.
Sully, we good?
You ready?
All right, kids. On me.
All right.
We're gonna ease on outta here.
[sobbing]
- On me. On me.
- [Lo'ak] Keep back.
Keep moving.
- [shouting]
- [gasps]
- [snarls]
- [groaning]
[shouts]
No!
Dad!
[Tuk] Dad!
[Wainfleet] Come on.
Move.
- [Wainfleet grunting]
- [raiders ululating]
- No!
- [Tuk] Dad!
- Dad.
- Dad! Dad!
[breathing heavily]
- [shouts]
- [groaning]
[raiders laughing]
[snarls]
You are strong,
Sky Man.
[Tuk whimpers]
You...
show me how to make thunder.
[Quaritch] ...and that's
the magic.
See?
And now you take aim.
What do you want to hit?
Well, just go like this.
[raiders gasp]
Yeah.
Go on.
[grunts]
Feels good, doesn't it?
Uh-huh.
[Varang, raiders ululating]
I do not need you now, Sky Man.
[raiders chuckling]
- Bind him well.
- On your knees.
- Prepare for sacrifice.
- [raiders ululating]
You, you. Come with me.
Clear the way!
Neytiri!
[Neytiri breathes shakily]
Cut her down. Cut her down. Hold her.
[shushes] Neytiri, we got you.
- You're gonna be okay. Okay?
- [Neytiri coughs]
[Norm] We got you.
Max, prep for surgery. Go.
Open both doors.
[cheering, chanting]
[chanting in Na'vi]
[grunting]
[straining]
[Jake groans]
These pricks know their knots.
[chanting in Na'vi]
[grunts]
[♪ mysterious music plays]
[breathing heavily]
[hisses]
[grunting, choking]
[whooping, ululating]
[choking, gagging]
[grunts]
- [speaking Na'vi]
- [grunts]
[chanting continues]
[panting, grunting]
Guys, come on.
[grunts]
- Come on.
- Move it. Move it!
[whooping]
[clamoring]
It was the girl.
Come on. Get in.
This way.
Let's go.
Come on.
- [whooping]
- Through here.
Tsahìk.
They are gone.
We search by air.
[speaking Na'vi]
Tarsem.
What? Oh.
Easy, easy. Max!
- Be still, child.
- Okay. No, no, no.
No. Stop it. Stop her.
- Daughter.
- My children.
- Neytiri, be calm.
- My children!
Daughter, calm.
My children.
The children.
Where?
[breathing shakily]
Where are they?
[insects chirping]
[Tuk grunts]
Come on. Let's hustle.
Max, get me in.
- [Max] Yeah, yeah.
- Are we hot?
We're hot.
All right. Don't even calibrate.
[grunts]
No. You must rest, my child.
- [grunts]
- Daughter.
- [Max] Good luck.
- Thank you.
[straining] I will ride.
Come.
No. No.
[insects chirping]
[Spider] I'm okay.
I'm okay to walk.
[pants, grunts]
I've got you.
[breathing shakily]
[Spider] This is good.
[Tuk mumbles]
[Kiri] Lie down.
[grunts, sighs]
We're clear.
Yeah.
Which brings us to our...
unresolved issues.
Well, I'm out of arrows.
Still got our knives.
Yeah, well I'm kind of tired.
[chuckles] Yeah.
Yeah, better save it.
In case those...
flying monkeys show up.
[breathing heavily, sighs]
Yeah, sure.
[insects chirping]
[Quaritch] You and the missus
must have done
something right,
I'll give you that.
He's a good kid.
[♪ hopeful music plays]
Yeah, he's a great kid.
[chuckles]
Hey, uh, this don't mean
we're going to start
taking long walks together.
I'm still bringing you in.
Dead, if I have to.
All this time out here
and you still don't get it.
This world goes much deeper
than you imagine.
You witnessed it tonight.
With her.
And with him.
Don't matter.
It don't matter what color I am.
I still remember
what team I'm playing for.
You got new eyes, Colonel.
All you got to do is open them.
[sighs]
[ikran shrieks]
It's them.
It's the Ash.
Get up. Come on.
We got to move. Let's go.
- Come on. Come on.
- Come on.
Come on. We got to move.
[ululating]
It's okay. It's okay.
They're ours.
[whooping]
Tarsem! [whoops]
- Jake.
- [Kiri] Tarsem.
Kiri, Tuk, are you hurt?
[Kiri] How did you find us?
[Neytiri] Children!
- [Lo'ak] Mother.
- [Tuk] Mama.
Tuk. Tuk. Kiri.
Lo'ak.
- [Jake] Hey.
- Jake.
Are you okay? [sobs]
Come here. It's okay.
We're okay.
[Spider] Hey, Norm.
[♪ hopeful music plays]
What's up?
What?
What...
Dude.
Oh.
Yeah, I'm good
on the whole air thing.
[♪ majestic music plays]
[shrieks]
[gasps] Tuktirey.
[chuckles] Kiri.
Iron Sky, Blue One actual.
We're inbound
at the city wall.
[music ends]
[machines beeping]
So, you think
he's still with Sully?
I'd make book on it.
This is not my priority.
My priority is getting
this city built
and sending back amrita
to pay for it.
And who do you think
sets your priorities, General?
It's the big-picture guys.
So here's a big-picture
concept for you.
How are we supposed
to colonize this world
if we can't breathe
the fricking air?
You want to find the boy,
you got to find Sully.
- And I'm there.
- [grunts] Ow. Ow.
How many more of these, huh?
Not many more.
That's what you said yesterday.
Don't be a baby.
Here's the most recent scan.
Now, you see this?
This is all mycelium.
It's basically the same thing
as the forest network.
Somehow,
it colonized him,
spread through his entire system
and then made changes
at the cellular level.
I mean, look.
It altered his blood chemistry,
his nervous system, his lungs.
Can you get it out?
No, it's an endosymbiont.
We think they're keeping
each other alive.
It could kill him
if we even try.
But look.
I mean, he's...
he's alive.
- He's healthy.
- [beatboxing]
Maybe this is a good thing.
A good thing?
[sighs]
What if the RDA labs
could reverse engineer this?
What if every human being on Earth
could live here without a mask?
[clicks tongue]
Uh, Jake,
there's something else.
Sit. Hey, bud.
Hey.
- Okay, let me see.
- [Spider] Hey.
Hold-Hold still. Hold still.
You're fine.
- Look at that.
- [Spider grunts]
What are you doing?
What is that?
He's growin' a kuru.
- Wait, what?
- Oh, yeah.
[voices chanting,
speaking in Na'vi]
[voices stop]
Great Mother,
are you there?
Please.
Hear my small voice.
I prayed to you in the forest
to save my friend.
I prayed so hard.
But you didn't come.
You didn't answer.
So I had to do it myself.
I don't know how I...
I...
I asked the roots to help me.
I don't remember how I...
Please, no.
No, don't shut me out.
Why am I like this?
How am I doing these things?
Please, just talk to me.
Please.
No, no.
Please, please.
[sobs] No. No.
No. No!
[gasping]
[♪ mysterious music plays]
[grunting]
[birds chirping]
- [Norm] EEG is fine.
- [Jake] It's blinking. So...
That's blood pressure.
That's normal.
You want that blinking.
- Let's take these off.
- [Neytiri] Kiri.
- Run more tests.
- Eywa never came to me.
I told you.
I don't know how I did it.
Drink.
Kiri.
My child, you are touched
by the All Mother's hand.
This we have known
since you were born.
[♪ pensive music playing]
[sighs]
There's something you're hiding.
I have felt it
my whole life.
Just tell me the truth.
Please.
Tell her.
It is time.
My child.
You do not
have a father, Kiri.
What?
You...
Your... Your mother,
Grace's avatar,
now, when she was pregnant,
Norm ran some tests.
And it was a path...
pathelo...
A-A parthenogenic birth.
You're genetically identical
to the avatar.
There literally is no father.
[breathes shakily]
I'm a clone?
Granddaughter.
It was the will of Eywa.
When the dreamwalker body
lay here
in the Great Mother's hands...
[echoing]
...a seed was planted.
[♪ chanting in Na'vi]
[chanting stops]
[scoffs]
That really sucks.
That makes me
even more of a freak.
No, granddaughter.
You are Eywa's child.
[sighs]
[Jake] I don't care
how it happened.
- [sighs]
- You're my baby girl.
And I'm the only father
you'll ever need.
[sighs]
If I am so special,
why does Eywa
fold her ears to me?
Look, we don't know why,
but you're locked out from her.
It's some kind of firewall.
Yeah, it's like an encryption.
The harder you try to break in,
the harder it fights back.
Eywa has a path for you.
Though she chooses
to conceal it,
you must trust in her.
I have to find out what it is.
No, you have to stop asking.
Kiri, if...
if you try to connect again,
you could die.
You do it underwater,
and you will die.
[sighs]
[Jake] He can't stay here.
If the RDA get him...
well, we'll never stop 'em.
If he is so dangerous,
to The People, to everything,
we should just kill him.
[chuckles] It's Spider.
He'll come with us.
He'll come
to the reef.
We can protect him there.
Toruk Makto knows best.
Oh, come on, baby.
- It's not like that.
- [sighs]
It is decided.
Thirty meters.
Get me up in there.
Get me in the pocket.
Get me in the pocket
with the rocket.
Ten meters.
Here we go. And...
[shrieks]
[bellows]
Lung shot.
She's bleeding out.
[tulkun shrieks]
Whoo!
[tulkun wailing]
[ikran screeches]
A new demon ship has come.
Bigger.
More of our tulkun
have been killed.
I'm so sorry, Brother.
Jakesully,
the outcast is stirring up
the young bulls.
Our tulkun
have called for council
to decide about him.
You must rest.
This must be removed.
See me.
Kids. Kids, on me.
[groans]
[strains, wails]
[shouts, groans]
[Kiri chuckling]
No, I'm serious.
When it grows long enough,
I'm going to get my own ilu.
Skxawng.
You need a very small ilu.
[Spider] Just you watch,
I'm going to
get my own skimwing.
- Oh, a skimwing?
- Then I'll be the one laughing.
So, how is this?
Your daughter,
your half-blood daughter,
with no training...
- Hold here.
- [groans]
...has done what
no Tsahìk could do?
Who are you to question
the will of Eywa?
I am Tsahìk!
Then be Tsahìk!
These herbs do nothing!
Herbs from my forest
heal faster.
I tell you to rest.
You do not rest.
Then you blame my herbs.
Hold still.
[groans]
Stupid woman.
Careful, Tsahìk,
or I may forget
that you are with child.
- [snarls]
[scoffs]
[tulkun rumbling]
[Tonowari]
The matriarch has spoken.
She says the outcast continues
to defy the tulkun way.
All killing is forbidden.
He was outcast for this,
but he has done it again.
The outcast attacked
a demon ship,
bringing death to our people.
Even the son
of Toruk Makto.
Dad, they can't blame
Payakan for that.
Not now.
[matriarch rumbling]
She says he continues
to disrupt,
spreading bad ideas
among our young.
[matriarch rumbling]
- It's bullshit.
- It's not true.
[Tonowari]
She says he will only
bring more death.
Hey, why don't you
say something?
Just say something.
Please.
[rumbling]
She says the outcast
may not stay in
these waters.
- He must go far...
- No.
...where his Song
cannot be heard.
Exiled for life.
That's not fair.
It is decided.
[Payakan singing]
You will never hear my Song again.
No! Payakan!
Brother! Please.
- No. Payakan!
- No.
[Lo'ak] Brother!
[Payakan moaning, whistling]
This is...
This is wrong!
You do not
speak here.
No.
Payakan fought for us.
- He fought for us.
- Lo'ak.
He saved your daughter's life.
- This is council.
- He saved her life!
- You do not speak.
- He defends us.
- This is council.
- Lo'ak.
The elders have spoken.
The tulkun are being hunted.
They're dying.
Lo'ak, that's enough.
No!
- Lo'ak speaks the truth!
- No, Tsireya.
- No!
- [Tonowari] Daughter!
- Payakan is a warrior!
- Tsireya.
He fought for us.
- More than you. Or you.
- [clamoring]
More than any of you!
- He fought for us!
- [Tonowari] Sit down!
Lo'ak.
- Take him from here!
- You do not speak here, boy.
- Make a hole.
- [Kiri] Dad!
Listen to him!
[Tonowari] We are in council!
The elders have spoken.
- [shouts]
- What are you doing?
You never stand up for me!
- [Tonowari] Be seated.
- Come with me.
[Tonowari] Council continues.
[breathing heavily]
We're at war.
You understand that?
If you disobey orders,
people get killed.
With Spider here, we're trying
to keep a low profile.
But that rogue is out there.
He's stirring up
the young bulls.
He was going to bring
the whole RDA down on us.
You want him gone.
That's why
you didn't say anything.
He's a loose cannon.
He's just like you.
In fact, if you hadn't gone
to him in the first place,
if you hadn't disobeyed orders,
then your brother
would still be...
[breathes shakily]
That wasn't my fault.
Dad, that...
That's not my fault!
[crying]
Lo'ak.
[breathes shakily]
[sighs] Go to him, Jake.
Or you will lose another son.
I've got nothing to say to him.
Do not blame Lo'ak.
You said you could
protect this family.
That, you could do.
Yeah, I thought
we would be safe here.
Our son is dead, Jake.
I was wrong!
What do you want me to say?
That every decision that I made
for this family is wrong?
I killed our son?
And still we are here
in this place,
hiding this pink skin,
this alien.
If I had to choose
between my family
and a pink skin,
I would kill him
right now. [inhales sharply]
Stop, stop, stop.
We're not doing this.
Look.
You already chose
between your family
and a pink skin once,
remember?
You cannot live like this, baby.
In hate.
I hate them, Jake.
I hate them.
[breathes heavily]
I hate their pink little hands.
I hate the insanity
in their minds.
I'm a human.
Inside.
You hate me?
I'll always be an alien
to you, won't I?
Doesn't matter how long
I live in this skin.
Do you hate your children?
With their alien hands?
No.
Are you ashamed
every time they make a mistake,
every time they're different?
That's because of
the human inside them, right?
Yes.
[breathing shakily]
[breathes deeply]
I'm sorry, baby.
I'm sorry.
We have to stand strong
right now.
This family is our fortress.
[breathing heavily]
The People say
that when you touch steel,
its poison
seeps into your heart.
[breathing shakily]
[yells, breathing heavily]
[crying]
Lo'ak!
Brother.
Lo'ak.
Stay in this life, Brother.
[breathes heavily]
We need you.
We love you.
You have greatness in you.
[crying]
[Kiri sighs]
The strength of the
ancestors is here.
A bow can be fixed.
[breathes deeply]
[groans, strains]
Good. Good.
Moment of truth.
[whistles]
Whoa. [chuckles]
Go.
- [chuckles]
- You feel her?
Hell yeah.
I got fins.
[chuckling]
Yeah, you do.
- Whoo!
Go, Monkey Boy!
Whoo!
You. Face down!
Eyes on the ground.
Stay calm, my people.
Stay calm.
[screams, groans]
Spider. Huh?
I think we're wasting
our time, Colonel.
- They don't know anything.
- Oh, they know.
They're just not talking.
We got one more play,
but it's radical.
[♪ tense music plays]
[breathing heavily]
- [Mangkwan ululating]
- [grunts]
[grunts]
Hey, you remember me,
don't you? [groans]
[grunts] Whoa, whoa, whoa.
- Mine!
- Just relax.
- Get him up.
- I brought something for your Tsahìk.
- You take me to your Tsahì...
- Move!
- Hey, hey!
No need to do that.
- I got my eye on you.
- Keep going.
[Mangkwan chanting, whooping]
- [Quaritch grunts]
- [horn blowing]
[Mangkwan warrior] Move!
Tsahìk.
What is he doing here?
[Mangkwan warrior 2] Tsahìk.
[grunts]
I'll get you as many
as you want.
[warriors snarling]
What is your name, Sky Man?
Quaritch.
Colonel Miles Quaritch.
[Varang] Hmm.
You touch me with that
thing again, I'll kill you.
You will kill no one.
[chuckling]
Lady, I'm gonna beg to differ.
- Drop him.
- [gunshot echoes]
- [hisses]
- [Mangkwan clamoring]
Good trick...
Quaritch.
You're next, cupcake.
So think careful
about what you want to do.
Come.
We will talk inside.
What are you doing, boss?
[chuckles]
Cozy.
See, thing is...
everybody's lying to me.
They say that
you can make a stone
speak the truth.
You seek a man,
the other Sky Man like you.
Not like me.
No, he's a traitor.
Well, then he must die.
[chuckles]
Varang can help you
find this man.
And the other you seek.
This...
air breather.
[Quaritch chuckles]
[Varang] First,
I must see your soul.
[groans]
Be still.
[echoing] Be still.
[blows]
[grunts] Whoa.
[chuckles] Whoa. Whoa.
[♪ eerie music plays]
[Quaritch] Whoa.
That's some strong shit.
This...
is the only pure thing
in this world. [echoes]
[chuckles]
The fire came from the mountain
when I was little.
[echoing] Burned our forest.
It took everything.
My people were starving.
They cried for help.
But Eywa did not come.
So I went to the fire.
And I learned its way.
I am the fire.
By my hand,
my people grow strong.
We do not lie down and die
just because Eywa
- turns her back on us.
- [grunts]
We turn our back on Eywa,
a weak mother
for weak children.
[Quaritch breathes heavily]
We do not suck
on the breast of weakness.
Now...
only true words
will come from your tongue.
Mmm.
[sighs]
You have a strong heart.
No fear.
[grunts] Ow.
[chuckles] Ow.
That wasn't cool.
I will eat your heart, Quaritch.
Oh. [laughing]
But first, you will answer me.
Why are you here?
I'm here for you.
You wish to serve me?
I don't serve anybody.
I need you.
Well, I do not need you.
But I might keep you
as my slave
to pleasure me.
That sounds like
a fun weekend, but...
that's not what you really want.
And what do I want?
What you've never had.
An equal.
You want to spread your fire
across the world.
Yeah.
I'll give you guns.
I'll give you comms.
RPGs.
Oh, that's strong magic.
Command from a distance,
strike like lightning.
The clans...
as far as you can fly,
they'll bow down before Varang.
[Varang breathing sharply]
You want to take on Eywa...
you need me.
I See you.
Damn right you do.
- [Quaritch chuckles]
- [Varang gasps, laughs]
[laughs]
[whooping, clamoring]
[♪ majestic music plays]
[sighs]
When I can connect again,
someday,
whenever,
I can be your guide
in the Spirit World.
Well, can I just go now?
No.
- Not without me.
- [chuckles]
A Sky Person can't just show up.
It'd freak out the ancestors.
[bellows]
They're starting to arrive
for the Calf Communion.
[bellows]
Yearling calves
and reef babies together
having their first bond
with Eywa.
It'll be so beautiful.
[bellows]
- [bellows]
- [moans]
[grunting, sighing]
[Metkayina celebrating
in distance]
Let me see.
Looks good.
I like this on you.
Come to the festival.
No, no, no, no.
Then I will just
stay here with you.
Lo'ak, I should not
tell you this, but...
my tulkun Sister says
they have been hearing Payakan,
very faint,
calling to his birth clan.
Where?
Tulkun Song travels very far
through the water, Lo'ak.
Please.
[inhales sharply, whimpers]
[sobs]
[sighs]
Lo'ak.
Bye, Mom.
Where are you going?
Just out.
There's something I have to do.
[breathes shakily]
[Tsireya] Lo'ak!
Lo'ak!
Lo'ak, wait!
Lo'ak.
[sighs]
Yes, we must find
Brother of Payakan.
- [squeaking]
- [clicking]
We cannot go.
The Calf Communion
is in five days.
I have to go.
This is my fault.
We are going.
All of us.
- Get weapons and food.
- [bellows]
Tell no one.
[rider ululating]
Our children have gone
to look for him.
You let them?
They did not ask.
All right, we'll get the riders.
We'll go after them.
We cannot search
the whole ocean.
We need the warriors here
for Calf Communion
if the demon ships come.
My boy is out there by himself.
He will come back
when he is ready.
This is his path.
Look at what he did.
Jake, the strength
of the ancestors
runs in your son's veins.
You must trust that.
The way of water
has no beginning...
and no end.
The sea is your home...
before your birth...
and after your death.
[gasping]
[screams]
[groans, breathing heavily]
[gasps]
Where is the one
they call Toruk Makto?
How many fish are in the sea?
One, two.
How many birds are in the sky?
One, two, three...
[both laugh]
I mean, come on,
you couldn't have asked Eywa
to make me a little bit taller?
Maybe even
a little bit more blue.
No.
I was busy saving your life.
[chuckles] Skxawng.
Just a little bit.
A couple of centimeters.
She's the All Mother.
She can do anything.
You are perfect
just the way you are.
Come on, Monkey Boy.
[chuckles]
So next thing is,
I'm going to learn
how to ride a skimwing.
So you can become
a mighty warrior
and protect us all.
Hey, it's not the size
of the dog in the fight,
it's the size of the fight
in the dog.
What is it?
[Kiri gasps]
Sh... [grunts]
[warriors whooping, shouting]
[Spider] Run!
Run!
[Mangkwan grunting, whooping]
- [panting]
- [Kiri grunting]
[breathing heavily] Hurry!
[Spider] Go. Go!
[panting] Spider.
Over here, assholes!
[whooping]
[Spider] Come on!
Hey, skxawng!
This way, you bastards!
Come on, dipshits!
Is that all you got?
[whooping continues]
Shit!
- Hey, hey!
- [straining]
Settle down there, cowboy.
Careful with that knife.
That's how people get hurt.
- [gasps]
- [Spider grunts]
Air breather.
[screaming]
[snarls]
[groans, grunts]
[grunts]
[snarls]
We fly.
- Break off.
- [whoops]
Dragonfly, Blue One.
You are cleared in.
[nightwraiths shrieking]
[breathing heavily]
- What is it?
- [Neytiri] Tuk!
[♪ dramatic music playing]
They're blocking us in.
Weapons up.
Weapons!
Where's your sister?
She went for water.
Where's Kiri?
Where's Spider?
- [horn blows]
- Dad!
- Where's Spider?
- They took him.
The blue colonel took him.
Take him.
[roars]
[shrieks]
Be calm.
No fear.
No fear!
Jake Sully!
Take the girls, and you go now!
I will not go without you.
No. They got Spider.
There's nothing
holding them back.
You've seen what they can do.
These people will die.
You cannot ask this.
Husband, I cannot.
This is the only way.
[Quaritch] Jake Sully!
Show yourself!
[Jake] You got to go.
You got to go right now.
Take your sister. Go and hide.
Go!
[whimpers]
If you stay, I stay.
I will kill many!
Whatever happens,
do not raise that bow.
You swear to me.
[breathes heavily]
I know he's here.
Give him to me.
- [Ronal breathing shakily]
- He is Metkayina.
He is one of us.
He is one of us!
Burn something.
Dragon 2-4,
lay down some incendiary
- on the center village.
- [pilot] Copy.
Switching incendiaries.
[Metkayina screaming, clamoring]
[Mangkwan cheering, ululating]
I want Jake Sully!
Stop. No.
Hold your fire.
Hold your fire. Stop.
Hold fire.
Copy.
Breaking off.
This is my path, Brother.
[sighs]
[hisses]
[snarls]
Colonel.
Corporal.
You take me,
and you leave my family
and these people alone.
Not good enough.
Going to need the missus too.
[Jake] You get me.
Both of you or I
hammer this place flat.
Pregnant ladies, kids.
I'll blow grandma's skinny shit
through the back of the hooch
'cause I just don't care.
And my pals here, well,
they're just dying
to waste everybody
and take some scalps.
[Mangkwan whooping]
[hissing]
- Really?
- [hisses]
We doing this?
When I drop my arm,
you and your new girlfriend die.
You in particular die a lot.
I die, everybody here dies.
Maybe.
I think you can get some
of us but not all of us.
Maybe we bum rush ya,
and your gunships hesitate
'cause we all look the same.
And then when you're begging
- for your life...
- [chuckles]
...I'll scalp you.
Well, damn, Corporal.
I don't know if you're smart
or just shit nuts.
You never struck me
as all that smart.
[warriors chuckle]
I need your word,
marine to marine.
Safety
for these people.
Burn them all, Quaritch.
[♪ tense music plays]
[snarls]
Do we have a deal?
[music ends]
Done.
Want to pinky swear?
[breathing heavily]
[Quaritch] Take him.
Turn around.
[Neytiri breathing heavily]
Move.
[yells]
[breathing heavily]
- Let's go.
- Come on.
Another time then,
Mrs. Sully.
[snarls]
Saddle up.
- [Mangkwan whooping]
- [warrior grunts]
[breathing shakily]
[beeping]
What do we got?
Ma'am, we have a big incursion.
- Banshee riders inbound.
- I see that.
- So light 'em up.
- I can't, ma'am.
Weapons locked out.
They all have IFF badges.
Expand it.
Echo 1-6, intersect the target.
[shrieks]
[roars]
[crowd clamoring]
[breathing heavily]
[in Na'vi] Stand up straight, you idiots.
Do not show fear.
[scientist, in English]
All right. All right.
- Hold him there.
- [grunting]
Easy, easy.
Let's go.
- [Spider] Jake!
- [soldier 1] Grab him.
[soldier 2] Let's go. Move.
- Jake! Jake!
- Bring him in.
- [radio chatter]
- [chuckles]
Jake!
[soldier 3] Up.
[grunts]
Mission accomplished, General.
Jake Sully.
Toruk Makto himself.
[clamoring]
[breathing deeply]
It's not enough for you
to hand out guns,
you've got to bring hostiles
inside the perimeter.
[speaks Na'vi]
[in English] Not hostiles.
Allies.
General Ardmore,
I'd like you to meet Varang,
Tsahìk of the Mangkwan.
Let me make this very clear,
Colonel Cochise,
I want every one
of these savages
escorted off my base
ASAP,
including your little
missy over here.
[sighs]
[inhales deeply]
Don't be a jackass, General.
Take the win.
We got him, people!
Huh? [chuckles]
End of an era!
Yeah!
Whoo!
Tsahìk.
[chuckles]
Let's go.
[♪ dramatic music plays]
[struggling, snarling]
[nurse] Easy, easy.
You'll just feel this
a little bit.
- Hold still.
- [Spider grunts]
[screams]
Almost there.
- Good. Hold it there.
- Another few seconds.
[growls]
Payakan!
[squeaks]
[narrating]
The People say
the sea washes you clean.
Payakan!
It's Lo'ak.
- It's him.
- Lo'ak.
- [Rotxo] It's him.
- Lo'ak!
[Aonung] Skxawng, over here.
Lo'ak!
Tsireya!
[honking]
[Lo'ak] They also say,
if you see the deep ones,
the Tsyong...
they're spirits
sent to judge you.
[squeaks]
- Tsyong!
- Go, go, go.
[gasps]
[grunts]
[grunting]
[straining]
[grunts]
[bellows]
[drowning]
[echoing] Lo'ak. Lo'ak.
Lo'ak! Lo'ak!
[coughing]
Tsireya.
- [coughs]
- [chuckles]
[sighs]
[chuckles]
[Tsireya] Thank you,
Great Mother.
Come on, let him breathe.
Let him go.
[breathing heavily]
Can't believe you guys
came after me.
[chuckles]
My friend's path is my path.
Is this your Sister?
Yes.
What about Payakan?
Does she hear him?
He is close.
He is coming now.
So, what have you got?
Uh, this mycelium that's
living inside his body...
Wait, there's something
living inside of him?
Yes, it's an endosymbiont.
It's somehow moderating
the ion exchange...
Okay, stop. I don't need
to know how it works.
I just need to know
if we can duplicate it.
[grunts]
[grunting]
Let me out of here,
you jerk-offs!
[gasps]
I told those rubber-gloved pukes
to lay off you for a while.
Where's Jake?
He's locked up,
where he belongs.
Here.
I brought you a burger.
You better not hurt him.
He's not part
of your life anymore.
You're with me now.
[chuckles]
I'm your father.
My father's dead.
[sighs] You're just
some made-up thing
they gave his memories to.
No, no. No.
I'm still me.
I checked.
Yeah, look.
"Colonel
Miles Quaritch."
[scoffs]
Deceased.
[inhales deeply, sighs]
You know, we didn't get a chance
to talk too much
when we were out in
the bush together, but, uh...
I gotta thank you.
I mean, you hauled me
out of a sunken ship.
You saved my life.
Yeah. Sure wish
I hadn't done that.
Maybe that's true.
Maybe, deep down, it isn't.
Either way,
I owe you.
And I gotta tell you that, uh...
Man, I'm proud of you.
You're an amazing kid.
You got...
guts, smarts, and...
Son, you've got the heart
of a lion. [chuckles]
I see myself in you.
Oh, yeah.
I tell you
who I really see in you,
and that's your mother.
[chuckles]
Oh, man.
She was, uh, ferocious.
Tough to live with, but...
I loved her.
And, man, did she love you.
Hardest thing she ever did
was climbing aboard
that gunship that day,
going into battle,
leaving her little baby behind.
[sighs]
Your mom died a hero, Son.
You got that
in you too.
Anyway,
I didn't come down here
to take a trip down memory lane.
I just came by to tell you
that I'm here for you.
If you need me.
I'm here for you.
Can I keep it?
Eat something, will you?
[Lo'ak] Brother!
[singing] I'm glad to see you.
I See you, Brother.
- [panting]
- [moans]
What is it?
What's wrong?
[rumbling] It is...
Very bad.
Didn't you find your birth clan?
[singing] I did.
But only one survives.
[singing] I am Ta'nok.
Look what they did to me!
Shot me!
Blinded me!
Look what the
Sky People did to me!
Tulkun are already coming in,
but the aggregation doesn't
peak until the eclipse,
which is the day after tomorrow,
and that's when we hit 'em.
No, no, hold on.
No...
- you're talking about wholesale slaughter.
- [Scoresby] Uh-huh.
Hundreds killed.
Entire pods just wiped out.
That's the beauty of the idea.
We'll fill a year's quota
in just one day.
These are intelligent,
soulful beings.
Who are you?
Ian... Ian Garvin.
Marine biologist.
These creatures,
they have culture,
they have music,
they have names for each other.
This is organized.
This aggregation is deliberate.
It's a spiritual gathering
for them...
Get off your high horse, Garvin.
We all made our deals.
No, I did not sign up for this!
[Ardmore] Dr. Garvin.
Dr. Garvin, thank you.
Your protest has been noted.
- Oh, it's been noted?
- [Ardmore] Yes.
Sub teams and fast boats,
you guys will form a cordon.
You'll drive the family groups
in here to where it forms
a natural choke point
against the islands.
[crowd member]
We got you, Sully!
I can't believe we got him.
[guard] Hey!
Make a hole.
[Quaritch] Open up.
[guard 2] Weapon, sir.
End of the line, Jake.
[sighs]
[Quaritch] Zero-six tomorrow.
Varang wants your heart,
but I'm going old-school.
Firing squad.
Selfridge says
it's a "better optic."
Yeah. Well, you be
a good dog for the suits.
This isn't about them.
[sighs]
It's about me and you.
About a marine
that betrayed my trust.
About the men and women I lost.
Dead man's memories.
Miles Quaritch
is gone.
You're free,
and there is a world out there.
There's things that those suits
will never understand.
The Na'vi call it kame, "to See."
[in Na'vi] I know what they call it.
Then learn to See!
Connect to something
greater than you...
...greater than anything
you've ever known.
[in English] And See this world.
See yourself.
I'll see you...
at zero-six.
[grunts]
[sighs]
[♪ suspenseful music plays]
[people in lab chattering]
[laughter]
Last time, I got two.
Yeah, but they were
the ugliest ones
in the village. [laughs]
[snarls]
[grunts]
Open. Watch him.
Hands on the wall. Hands on the wall.
[clamoring]
- All right, we're good.
- Close it. Go.
[beeping]
It's nothing. Just one
of Quaritch's scouts.
[beeping]
- [whispers] Watch for me.
- [growls]
[clamoring]
- [panting]
- [beeping]
Okay, you've got a PhD.
How hard can it be?
[clamoring, whooping]
[sighs]
[soldier 1] Ah,
it's not crazy, man. If I was
- four or five feet taller.
- [soldier 2] Yeah.
Felt the suckers, but
they're sharp as blades too.
They're not soft.
Guys, we're gonna go
grab drinks.
Check this out.
What's up, cutie?
[snarls]
[RDA soldiers laugh]
- She wants me.
- Ah.
What?
- [laughing]
- Hey. [shushes]
Quaritch.
[grunts]
We are the fire.
Mangkwan.
[speaking Na'vi, whooping]
Quaritch.
[whispers]
Make no sound, witch.
Where is Jakesully?
Ah, the wife.
Loyal to her man.
Speak or I cut.
[both grunting]
Where?
I will not ask again.
[snarls]
[exclaims] No, wait.
Wait. [breathes heavily]
Past the camp.
A cage for an animal.
Take me there.
Move. Which way?
[Quaritch] Hey, sugar!
[grunts]
[snarls]
- [snarls]
- [Quaritch] Join the party.
[snarls]
[♪ tense music plays]
[grunts]
Get after her.
I want her heart!
[Mangkwan ululating]
[panting, grunting]
- [exclaiming]
- [gunfire]
- [ikran shrieks]
- [grunts]
Go, go, go.
[♪ tense music continues]
[yells]
[guard] Take cover!
- Watch out.
- [guard] Clear the area!
[shouts]
[Neytiri] Jake!
General.
- Not now. I have a situation.
- No...
I have a situation.
The kid is loose,
and I need him back.
Alive.
- [shrieks]
- [gunfire]
Light her up.
[ululating, whooping]
[Neytiri shrieks]
[shouts]
[shrieks]
[gasps]
[gasps, breathes shakily]
[ikran shrieks]
[panting]
- [grunts]
- [shrieks]
[snarls]
[guard 1] Hey. Whoa.
Stop. Stop!
Out of the way, guys.
Move it.
[guard 3] Fire.
Hit him.
Out of the way, guys.
Blade down.
[grunts] Go, Jake.
Light him up.
[grunts]
Reverse.
[bullets ricocheting]
Gotcha.
Aim for the cameras.
Okay. Stay with me.
[panting]
Stay with me.
[breathing heavily]
What am I doing?
[clamoring, shouting]
[person] Go! Back up.
[breathing heavily]
Is my protest
noted now, fuckers?
Jake,
this way.
No. No, this way.
This way.
- Come on.
- Okay.
Ian Garvin, marine bio.
Oh.
- Come on.
- Hey, I-I gotta say,
I'm a real big fan
of everything you've done.
I'm more than a
little awe-inspired right now.
- The way that you...
- Shut up.
What's the plan?
This is as far as I'd got.
Well, then there's no plan.
Just Neytiri.
Come on.
[♪ tense music plays]
Go, go, go.
Go, go.
[breathing heavily]
Why are you doing this?
[panting] There's gonna be
a massive tulkun hunt
the day after tomorrow.
They're gonna hit them
with every ship they've got.
The Calf Communion.
You've got to stop them.
You're the only one who can.
Come on.
[panting]
[shrieks]
Sa'ata... [shushes]
Let's go.
[panting]
- Oh, God.
- Tuck in.
Go now. Go.
Oh, shit.
Damn it.
Go! Get out of here!
Oh, shit. [pants]
[pilot] Lima 1-6,
there's a subject
pinned down behind a vehicle.
- [soldier 3] Is that Sully?
- [soldier 4] He's pinned down.
Switch missiles.
Take him out.
Copy.
Switching missiles.
Hey, remember me?
That's right, pendejos.
Yeah.
I don't need this shit.
What are you gonna do?
You gonna shoot me?
The kid's with him.
The air breather.
- He's blocking my shot.
- Move, move.
Don't shoot.
Tell him not to shoot.
Lima 1-6, Blue One.
Hold your fire.
Keep visual on him.
1-6, hold your fire.
Get more assets
on that position.
Yeah, you're not gonna
shoot me. You know why?
Because you can't. [laughs]
You know what you can do though?
You can kiss my ass.
Yeah. Come on, Jake.
Go. What are you doing?
Come on. Go. Go.
Come on.
[pilot] He's moving west.
Maintaining a target lock.
The shot is not clear.
[♪ tense music plays]
Hey, stay on me.
[panting]
[grunts]
Stay close to me.
I'm not gonna play this game.
Lima 1-6, take your shot.
- No, don't shoot.
- Get him out of here.
Belay that. Hold your fire.
Go, go, go.
Lima 1-6...
- What are you doing, man?
- [Ardmore] Lima 1-6,
you are cleared hot.
Weapons free.
Unable. I've lost visual.
Coming around.
- He's coming back around.
- This way.
[Quaritch] This is
Blue One.
Check your fire.
[Ardmore] Lima 1-6,
you are cleared hot.
1-6, in hot.
[shouts]
[Jake] Down!
[♪ triumphant music plays]
- [shrieks]
- [grunts, exclaims]
Ma Jake. [grunts]
Neytiri.
Baby.
I don't know whether
to kiss you or yell at you.
You waste time.
[sighs]
Come on. Let's go.
[grunts]
- Let's go.
- [Neytiri shrieks]
Land anywhere.
[Neytiri sighs]
[Spider groans]
Man, I gotta take a huge leak.
You guys landed just in time.
[whispers] What is it?
Why are we stopping?
They didn't even
put a fly in this thing.
That's just dumb.
Good idea.
Drink first,
then piss in the stream.
What is it, Jake?
[whispering] I was wrong.
We can't protect him.
I've gotta take this stuff off.
It's itchy as hell.
Quaritch has this woman.
He can find us wherever we go.
They will get him.
They will study him.
And when humans
can breathe our air...
then they will spread
across this world,
and they will destroy
the forests,
the oceans, everything.
Just like on Earth.
Then the Na'vi people
will be gone.
- The tulkun will be gone.
- [breathing heavily]
And I can't let that happen.
Man. Are you hungry?
'Cause I'm starving.
You were right.
It has to be done.
Jake.
[sighs]
He saved your life.
[breathes shakily]
This is the only way.
[♪ tense music playing]
Spider...
Come here.
What's going on?
What is it?
Just come with me.
Come on. Let's go.
[breathing heavily]
Hey, stop for a second.
I gotta take a leak.
Just stay close.
Where are we going?
Be quiet.
[breathing heavily]
So, is this, like, a talk?
[sighs]
Come here.
Come on.
Go.
This'll work.
Kneel.
- No.
- Kneel down.
[Spider grunting]
Please.
Jake, please stop.
Eyes front. Don't move.
Please,
you don't have to do this.
- Shh!
- [breathes heavily]
Please.
Great Mother, are you here?
[Spider] You don't
have to do this.
Guide my hand.
[Spider] Please don't do this.
Give me strength.
Just stop.
Please stop. Please.
- Don't look at me.
- Please.
Don't look at me.
[inhales sharply]
Forgive me, Son.
I'll be good.
May your spirit go to Eywa.
- I promise.
- May your body
return to the forest...
[sniffles]
Please, Dad.
...to preserve
the Great Balance.
May the ancestors welcome you.
[sobbing]
[exhales sharply, exclaims]
Please.
May the ancestors hold you.
May they sing your Song.
I know I have to go to Eywa now.
It's okay.
But...
Do you...
Do you still love me?
With all my heart.
[♪ emotional music playing]
[both breathing shakily]
[grunts]
[Spider panting]
[breathing shakily]
[crying] Ma Jake. Ma Jake.
I See you.
Whatever happens,
it won't be this way.
[Neytiri breathing heavily]
Then we will find another way.
[♪ hopeful music playing]
[Lo'ak] My dad knew in his heart
there was only
ever one path.
[Jake breathes shakily]
[Lo'ak] No matter
how you imagine yourself,
as a father,
as a husband,
sooner or later,
you're back on it.
- [Toruk breathing heavily]
- [Jake exhales deeply]
[Toruk rumbling]
Hello, old friend.
[sighs]
[Lo'ak] Toruk loved my father.
[screeches]
[Lo'ak] It knew they were
greater together.
That when they flew,
there would be blood.
[Toruk screeches]
He is coming.
[♪ dramatic music plays]
[clan whooping]
[speaking Na'vi]
[roars]
Toruk Makto!
[clan grunts]
No, no, no. Just...
Please, stand.
Stand up. Please.
- Baby.
- Jake.
Please. It's okay.
It's okay.
Go now
to all the clans
within a day's ride
and tell 'em...
[sighs]
Tell 'em Toruk Makto
calls to them.
And you tell 'em...
the day has come.
[shouts]
[ululating]
[cheering]
[Lo'ak] And so it came to pass
that Toruk Makto returned.
My father united the clans
once again.
He made the great speeches.
Many arrows together
cannot be broken.
We cannot be broken!
[cheering]
[♪ inspirational music plays]
[Lo'ak] But he knew
that it wasn't enough.
Great Matriarch,
wise elders,
the Sky People are coming.
Here, today.
Right now.
To kill our tulkun families.
I beg you,
fight with us.
[rumbles]
She says,
"We respect Toruk Makto,
but our ways
are ancient."
[rumbles]
"We believe
that killing will only
bring more killing,
in an endless,
expanding spiral."
Hear my words.
The Sky People will never stop.
Not until the last
of the tulkun is hunted.
[bellows]
Lo'ak.
[Payakan]
My Brother must speak to the council.
[matriarch] Payakan! Go!
You cannot be here.
Stop.
Lo'ak, what are you doing?
You can't be here.
Dad, wait.
I am Brother of tulkun.
I have a right to speak.
Lo'ak speaks the truth.
You must listen.
Tsireya.
[rumbles]
She says,
"His Brother is outcast."
You have no standing here.
If he is outcast,
then I am outcast.
And I am outcast.
Daughter, silence.
No.
You will never see me again.
And I and my Brother
are outcast.
Aonung.
And we are
also outcast.
- [Neytiri breathes shakily]
- [rumbles, clicks]
She says,
"You may speak."
[Lo'ak] Hear my words.
My Brother returned
to his birth clan
to defend them,
but his clan was wiped out
by the demon ships.
Only Ta'nok survived,
because she fought back.
Come forward.
[♪ mournful music playing]
[sighs]
[exhales]
[Ta'nok wails]
Ta'nok says,
"I speak for the dead mothers
and the dead calves."
[Ta'nok moaning]
"I speak for my people
and all our Songs."
[wailing]
"Gone.
Forever."
[wailing]
She says,
"I am the last.
The blind witness to our end."
- [Ta'nok wails]
- [sniffles, sighs]
Ta'nok says,
"The tulkun way must change.
Payakan shows our path."
[rumbling]
[bellows]
"We must fight."
We must fight!
[rumbling]
What did she say?
They will decide.
Look at all of this.
I mean, there's hundreds of 'em.
And look at all these old ones.
And old is good.
They never stop growing,
which means more amrita.
And look at this mama.
She must be
100 meters.
You're briefing without me.
An oversight, I assume.
No, it was not an oversight.
After your fiasco with Sully,
you're done, Colonel.
You're confined to base
pending an investigation.
Negative on that. I need to roll.
Sully will be there,
which means that Spider
will be there as well.
Don't look at him.
He's one step away
from the brig himself.
Don't tell him
not to look at me.
What are you gonna do?
Call Daddy?
- You mean the chairman?
- That's enough.
I can still complete
this mission.
Look at you.
You're a disgrace
to your uniform.
Assuming you remember
what a uniform is.
You're grounded, Colonel.
Permanently.
[sighs]
[clan speaking Na'vi]
- [breathing heavily]
- Why are you here, girl?
To pray, Tsahìk.
[pants]
No, child.
Why did you come to us?
Perhaps
it was for this moment.
[inhales sharply]
Only a chosen one
may call
upon the Warrior Mother.
[inhales sharply, groans]
[groans]
Tsahìk.
You're having contractions.
I fear we will...
we will not survive this.
[breathing shakily]
Kiri.
Hear my words.
If there is something
you can do,
then you must do it.
You have a strong heart.
Here.
I'm riding with you?
No, I need you here.
[sighs]
I can't do this
unless I know you kids are safe.
You keep your post
no matter what happens.
You read me?
Lima Charlie, sir.
If your father and I
do not return,
you take Spider and the girls
and you go as far
and as fast as you can.
[♪ tense music playing]
[shouting, ululating]
[♪ music intensifies]
Holy shit.
[adjutant] General, this flux
is off the scale.
Keep a wide radius
from that flux devil.
That thing
will rip your face off.
Roger.
Gun runner coming right.
Okay, boys.
Let's make some bank.
Yeah. [laughs]
Let's go.
Let's do this.
Whoo!
Sub teams, get wet.
Yeah, baby.
Let's do this.
See any hostiles?
Negative. No movement.
And the big guys
are just doing their thing.
Fish in a barrel, Scoresby.
Hold.
[Neytiri exclaiming]
Just hold.
Hold.
[breathes heavily]
Hang on.
There's no bulls
and no big females.
There's no elders.
Hold up, everybody.
Sir, I got a big signature.
Tulkun. Big ones.
Lots of big ones.
Multiple tulkun inbound.
Scoresby, I thought you told me
they're not aggressive.
Well, they're not.
Generally.
[matriarch] Payakan, I will lead.
[Payakan] Yes, Matriarch.
I've lost visual.
[roars]
[screaming, grunting]
Dude, they're fighting.
Yes! Yes!
- [roaring]
- [shouting, screaming]
[grunting]
This way. Get to the hatch!
[shouts]
[grunting]
[cheering, ululating]
Now!
[shouts]
- [Jake shouts]
- [ululating]
[♪ dramatic music playing]
[shouts]
[ululating]
Watch out!
[Neytiri ululates]
[cheering, ululating]
[Scoresby] Man your weapons.
Open fire.
[Neytiri ululating]
- [grunts]
- [shouts]
- [screeches]
- [exclaims]
[pants]
[roars]
Port side.
[shouts]
[wails]
Reload.
Watch out!
[screeching]
[screeches]
[grunts]
[splutters, grunts]
[shouts]
Yeah, Jake.
Bro, look.
- [alarm buzzing]
- [shouting]
[Spider] Yes!
Yeah!
[ululates]
[gasps]
- [Mangkwan ululating]
- Jake.
[♪ ominous music playing]
It's the Ash.
[crew member] Bogeys inbound.
Banshee riders.
Over a hundred.
They're friendlies.
They have IFF badges.
They're ours.
Thanks for getting Sully
out in the open, General.
I'll take it from here.
[shouts]
[rider screams]
[groans, breathes heavily]
[rider yelps]
[Lo'ak inhales sharply]
[rider shouts]
They can't win.
They're dying.
Kiri!
[Tuk] Kiri!
- [Spider] Stop her!
- Kiri. Kiri, stop.
- Kiri.
- Stop, stop, stop. Get back
to the shelter right now.
It's not safe out here.
I have to call
to the Great Mother.
If you connect underwater,
it'll kill you.
You can't do this.
We have to go.
No, Tuk. You can't be
out here right now.
Go. Get back.
- Kiri, wait. No, stop.
- Kiri, stop.
- Kiri!
- Kiri.
- [Tuk] Kiri.
- Come on.
- No, wait.
Crap, crap... Tuk, you stay back.
I mean it.
Lo'ak, come on.
Do not follow me.
[Spider] Come on.
[whimpering]
Lo'ak, they're coming.
Fight with us.
[Payakan] We must defend the Mothers.
Go. I'll stay with her.
Come on.
[whooping]
All Mother,
hear my words.
Please help us.
I beg you.
You are our only hope.
[Lo'ak screams]
[grunts]
[shouts]
- [grunts]
- [shouts]
[Kiri] Please.
We need you.
[grunts]
Don't push me away.
[♪ dramatic music plays]
Please don't.
No. Please, please.
[sobs] No, no, no.
Monkey Boy.
Let's do this.
Come on.
[Kiri grunting]
Fire.
[tulkun shrieking]
[grunting]
I beg you. Please.
No, please.
The People are dying.
- Please, no.
- [grunts]
- Tuk.
- [Tuk] Come on.
Come on.
We can do this.
Sullys never quit. [grunts]
[grunts, groans]
- [grunts]
- [ikran shrieks]
[snarls]
[shouts]
[grunts]
[exclaims, gasps]
Come on.
Let's go.
- [Kiri] Tuk.
- [Tuk] Come on.
[♪ dramatic music plays]
Great Mother, help us.
We beg you.
The People are dying.
I call upon the Warrior Mother.
You are our only hope.
[grunts]
[breathing heavily]
[snarls]
[grunts]
[shouts]
[Sa'ata shrieks]
[wails]
Fire.
[shrieks]
No!
[shouting]
That's him.
Get after him.
[groans]
Flank out.
Box him in.
[roars]
- [grunts]
- [shrieks]
[grunts]
[shouts]
[panting]
- [grunts]
- [shrieks]
[breathing heavily] Sa'ata.
Good girl.
[grunts]
[panting]
- [Spider] You okay?
- Yes. [pants]
Where's Kiri?
[breathing heavily]
[breathing heavily] Jake, I'm down.
Get to safety.
Do not attack.
We're done.
[breathing heavily]
No.
[sobs]
[♪ melancholy music plays]
Dad!
- Lo'ak.
- Dad.
- It's okay.
I got you.
[spluttering]
- [grunts]
- [gasps]
Tsahìk.
[spluttering continues]
[both straining]
You stay here.
I'm going back for her.
You can't leave me by myself.
[shrieks]
Sa'ata, wait.
[breathing heavily]
[whimpering, grunting]
I am dying.
No, you're not.
- [grunts]
- Why must you always argue?
I am... [grunts]
I am dying. [inhales sharply]
But first I will
push out this baby.
[Mangkwan whooping]
[shouts]
- [gasps, groans]
- [groaning]
Then push!
I got you.
[panting]
I'm gonna pull it on three.
Don't. Don't.
Just...
Just don't.
I gotta pack the wound.
[grunting]
[grunts]
[groans]
[panting] Kiri. Kiri.
Kiri.
[panting continues]
[grunts]
Are you okay?
- [mouthing] I'm okay.
- Good.
- [Ronal straining]
- Push, Tsahìk.
[shouts]
- You have one more push.
- [breathing heavily]
[straining continues]
[Neytiri] She is coming.
She is coming.
Take your child.
[both panting]
Thank you...
Neytiri.
Thank you.
[inhales sharply, sighs]
[Ronal whimpering]
What is her name...
She is...
She is Pril.
[whimpering continues]
Be strong.
Pril is a good name.
[whimpers]
You will protect her?
[breathing heavily]
Yes.
[exhales]
[♪ melancholy music plays]
[gunfire in distance]
[sighs] Dad, I'm...
I'm sorry I left my post.
- It's okay, Son.
- No.
You've proven yourself to me.
[breathing heavily]
I mean,
getting the tulkun to fight.
Toruk Makto couldn't do it,
and you did it.
I'm proud of you.
[rumbles, moans]
[moans]
[sobbing]
[screams]
[nightwraith shrieks]
Twenty-two, what's your status?
Casualties?
All right, people.
Let's get ourselves together.
We've still got work to do.
Seriously?
There's a hundred
billion dollars
waiting in that cove,
and nothing standing in our way.
Beers are on me.
Your name
is Pril.
Your mother was powerful.
You will be powerful too.
[Quaritch] Mrs. Sully.
[shouts]
[breathing heavily]
- [Tuk struggling]
- [Neytiri growls]
[shouts, panting]
Spoils of war.
Dad.
Dad, look.
- [Tuk] No!
- [Sa'ata shrieks]
[roars]
[grunts]
[panting]
I need you now.
By my side.
I need my wingman.
- Okay.
- Let's move out.
[grunts]
- [groaning]
- [Pril wails]
Jake, I know you're out there.
I know you can hear me.
Varang here's lighting up
your wife pretty good.
[shrieks, groaning]
No!
Now, I want you to come in,
and I want you
to bring Spider with you.
And I know you copy that.
- Thanks, baby.
- [grunts]
[pants]
[breathing heavily, grunting]
Picadors, get in there.
Go, go.
Go!
[tulkun whistling, squealing]
[wails]
They're trapping them.
Let's get those heifers
herded in tight.
[wailing continues]
A hundred meters.
Get me in there.
Get me in range.
[Spider] Shit.
Matadors, ahead slow.
Even spacing.
Sub teams,
torpedoes ready.
Arm torpedoes.
Arming one through four.
Torpedoes armed.
Sixty meters.
[gunner 3]
Target lock.
[tulkun rumbling, squealing]
Safeties off.
Stand by to fire.
[♪ dramatic music plays]
Look.
Hold your fire.
Hold fire for what?
We've got a situation down here.
It's Eywa. It worked.
It worked.
Go to the Sky People...
Kill them!
Kill them all!
[♪ dramatic music continues]
Look out!
[gunner 3] Get us out of here.
[shouting]
[screams]
[crew member 1] Whoa.
[crew member 2] Look out!
[screaming, clamoring]
Go, go.
Hit it.
All boats back to the ship.
All boats back
to the ship.
Yeah.
That's right, buttholes.
[roars]
[ikran shrieks]
[shouting]
[whooping, ululating]
- [roars]
- [shouts]
[screaming]
Oh, God.
[roars]
- [alarms blaring]
- Get us out of here.
Can't.
Propulsion's down.
[sighs]
[rumbles, bellows]
[breathing heavily]
[exclaiming, screaming]
[Scoresby screams]
[screaming]
[crew member] I need power.
Get me back up.
[alarms blaring]
[adjutant] General,
flux devil's pulling us in.
Abandon ship.
Abandon ship!
[alarm blaring]
[Lo'ak breathes heavily]
Stay close.
Clear.
[gunfire in distance]
[Jake] Tuck in.
[crew] Get to the lifeboats.
Get off the ship.
Run!
[Varang speaking Na'vi]
Okay. I'll need
covering fire.
Okay.
I'm gonna push left,
down the port side
and get around behind them.
Get eyes on me.
- Just watch me.
- Yes, sir.
And don't shoot anyone you love.
Go, go.
[grunts, breathing heavily]
[gunfire]
Colonel, this is Spider.
I'm here.
Don't kill them.
Where are you, boy?
Step out now.
[ship crew member screams]
All right.
I'll come out.
[Varang chanting in Na'vi]
[grunts]
[Quaritch] Spider!
Do you hear me?
We're running out of time.
[chanting in Na'vi continues]
[whispers] Come on.
[Mangkwan] Tsahìk.
- [warriors whooping]
- [Varang exclaiming]
I'm here to make a deal.
Me for them.
[Quaritch] That can happen.
Come with me, Son.
I'm a man of my word.
We can resolve this
here and now.
Everybody goes home.
Circle up.
We're out of here.
[breathes deeply]
[♪ tense music plays]
[grunting]
[shouts]
[grunts] Tuk.
[exclaims]
[both grunting]
Come on, Tuk.
- [Varang shouts]
- [Neytiri screams]
- [grunts]
- [screams]
[shouts]
[groans]
[echoing]
Leave my mother alone.
- [grunting]
- [Neytiri coughs]
[panting]
Bitch!
- [shouts]
- [whimpers]
[pants]
[panting]
[roars]
[grunts]
- [shrieks]
- Hyah.
Go find your mother.
Get her off the ship.
[whoops]
[grunting]
[whooping]
[grunts, panting]
Hang on, kid.
[breathing heavily]
[shrieks]
[both grunting]
Spider, here.
Jake!
[grunts] Spider.
[groans]
[panting, grunts]
[grunting]
Jake.
Spider.
[exclaims]
- [grunts] Go.
- Grab on.
Go, go!
[whoops]
[snarls]
Shit.
[grunting, gasping]
[Spider] Jake! Jake!
[exclaims]
[grunting]
[grunts]
[snarls]
I'll kill you!
I swear!
You gonna kill your own father?
Do not test me.
Give me that.
- [snarls]
- [groans]
You little bastard!
Come on.
Jake, come on.
[Quaritch groans]
Get out of here.
Go on.
[groans]
[panting, grunts]
[both grunting]
[strains]
Oh, shit.
[grunting continues]
[Jake, Quaritch
panting, grunting]
Jake!
Son!
[shouts]
Spider, no!
Hand him up.
Come on.
[all straining]
Pull me up.
- Come on.
- [straining continues]
If you hadn't've
shot me in the arm...
[snarls]
I oughta let you go.
Then do it,
Dad.
You're some piece of work, kid.
Pull us up.
Take my hand.
[all grunting]
Jake.
[Jake] Come on.
We got you.
[all panting]
[Jake groans]
[Quaritch groans]
[chuckles]
Well, this is awkward.
[Jake, Quaritch chuckle]
Now what?
We all gonna
hold hands and sing?
I "learn to See"?
You have a choice.
[ikran shrieks]
- Wait.
- [snarls]
- Wait. Wait.
- [Neytiri snarls]
- [Jake] Wait. Wait.
- [Tuk snarls]
[snarls]
Ain't this a bitch?
[♪ dramatic music plays]
[snarls]
[screams]
- [grunts]
- Dad, Dad.
Ma Jake, s-sit.
Come here. [sighs]
[sighs]
[♪ gentle music plays]
[Lo'ak]
The light always returns.
[♪ uplifting music plays]
[tulkun whistling, rumbling]
[Lo'ak] We all connect
with the Great Mother...
who holds all her children
in her heart.
New life keeps
the energy flowing...
like the breath of the world.
My Brother's voice was heard.
[Payakan rumbles]
[Lo'ak] He was accepted
by the clan.
In the Spirit World,
we call upon the strength
of the ancestors.
All those who have
walked the path before us.
[whooshing]
Come on, Monkey Boy. Come on.
[Kiri] Go on. Go on.
Sir.
I See you.
- Bro.
- Whoa.
Skxawng. [chuckles]
I'm happy to see you,
Little Bro.
Cuz.
Mom, this is Spider.
I've heard all about you.
Troublemaker.
[chuckles]
You are alive
for the first time.
And your spirit
will live in Eywa.
Forever.
You are one of us now.
You are one of The People.
No shit. [chuckles]
[all chuckle]
[♪ uplifting music continues]
[spirit voices whispering]
[♪ dramatic music plays]
♪ Our love
Will never fade away ♪
♪ We're diamonds in the dark ♪
♪ I put my head
Against your chest ♪
♪ And listen
To your heart ♪
♪ 'Cause you are my home
No matter where I go ♪
♪ Never alone
'Cause somehow I always know ♪
♪ Even through the flames ♪
♪ Even through the ashes
In the sky ♪
♪ Baby, when we dream
We dream as one ♪
♪ Every time I breathe ♪
♪ It's a song
To keep this love alive ♪
♪ I know when we dream
We dream as one ♪
♪ So beautiful
When we're together ♪
♪ Like feathers on a wing ♪
♪ Riding right beside me
We're two arrows in the wind ♪
♪ 'Cause you are my home ♪
♪ No matter where I go ♪
♪ Never alone ♪
♪ I've never been afraid
To let you know that ♪
♪ Even through the flames ♪
♪ Even through the ashes
In the sky ♪
♪ Baby, when we dream
We dream as one ♪
♪ Every time I breathe ♪
♪ It's a song
To keep this love alive ♪
♪ I know when we dream
We dream as one ♪
♪ Dream ♪
♪ Dream, dream, dream, dream ♪
♪ Dream, dream, dream ♪
♪ Even through the flames ♪
♪ Even through the ashes
In the sky ♪
♪ Baby, when we dream
We dream as one ♪
♪ Every time I breathe ♪
♪ It's a song
To keep this love alive ♪
♪ I know when we dream
We dream as one ♪
♪ Every time we dream
[♪ theme music playing]